Guide to the Morris Edward Opler papers, [ca. 1960-1996]
Opler, Morris Edward papers, [ca. 1960-1996]
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Morris Edward Opler papers, [ca. 1960-1996]
14-25-3238
Morris Edward, Opler 1907-1996
ca. 139 cubic ft.
Manuscripts, journal clippings, photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Research and office files documenting Opler's work, including his research on the myths and folklore of Apache tribes such as the Mescalero and the Jicarilla Indians.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of anthropology.
Professor of anthropology. Morris Opler was born in Buffalo, N.Y. on May 16, 1907. He received a B.A. in sociology from the University of Buffalo in 1929, an M.A. in anthropology there in 1930, and a Ph.D. from the University of Chicago in 1933. In 1931, he began fieldwork on the Mescalero Apache Reservation in New Mexico, as part of Ruth Benedict's summer field school. In 1932, he completed his dissertation, "An Analysis of Mescalero and Chiricahua Apache Social Organization in the Light of Their Systems of Relationship." From 1932-1937, he conducted fieldwork with various Apache peoples in New Mexico. He served as an assistant anthropologist with the Bureau of Indian Affairs from 1936-1937. He took a position at Reed College in Oregon from 1937-1938, then served as assistant professor of anthropology at Claremont College in California from 1938-1942. He received a Guggenheim fellowship from 1942-1943.
During World War II (from 1943-1944), Opler served as a social science analyst conducting wartime ethnographic research among Japanese internees with the War Relocation Authority in Manzanar, California,War Relocation Center. In 1944 he became a social science analyst with the Office of War Information in Washington, D.C. The following year he served as deputy chief and then chief of the Foreign Morale Analysis Division with the Office of War Information, where he stayed until 1946. He wrote three legal briefs defending Japanese American civil rights, two of which were heard before the U.S. Supreme Court.
After a visiting professorship at Howard University in the fall of 1945, Opler returned to academics for good in 1946. After teaching at Harvard University as an assistant professor from 1946-1948, he became professor of anthropology and South Asian studies at Cornell University, where he remained until 1969. He served as president of the American Anthropological Association in 1962-1963. After leaving Cornell, he went on to teach at the University of Oklahoma from 1969 until his retirement. He died on May 13, 1996, at the age of 88, in Norman, Oklahoma.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Research and office files documenting Opler's work, including his research on the myths and folklore of the Mescalero, Chiricahua, and the Jicarilla Apache, as well as the Lipan and Western Apache, the Kiowa, and the Navajo. Files relating to Cornell's South Asia Program and his research in India. Also files relating to the the Manzanar War Relocation Center in Owens Valley, California.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Opler, Morris Edward, 1907-1996
Subjects:
Anthropology--India.; Anthropology--Study and teaching.; Anthropologists--United States.; Apache Indians--Social life and customs.; Economics--India.; Ethnology; Indians of North America; Mescalero Indians--Folklore.; Jicarilla Indians--Folklore.; Jicarilla Indians--Rites and ceremonies.; Jicarilla Indians--Social life and customs.; Lipan Indians--Folklore.; Political science--India.; Sociology--India.
Places:
Senapur (India)--Economic conditions; India--Religious life and customs.; India--Social life and customs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Related collection: Japanese American relocation centers records, #3830.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Apache Indian Tribe
Subseries A: Research Items
Subseries B: Chiricahua
Subseries C: Mescalero
Subseries D: Jicarilla
Subseries E: Lipan
Subseries F: Western Apache
Subseries G: Kiowa
Series II. Navaho Indian Tribe
Series III. Miscellaneous Native American Material
Series IV. Morris Opler's Professional Material
Subseries A: 515- Anthropological Material
Subseries B: 301- Cultural Anthropology
Subseries C: 424- Comparative Religious Systems
Subseries D: 265- Culture and Personality
Subseries E: Course Notes
Subseries F: Unpublished and Miscellaneous
Subseries G: Theory: Tylor, Edward B.
Subseries H: Slides
Series V. Manzaner Japanese Internment Camp
Series VI. India
Subseries A: Gohana Kala
Subseries B: Senapur Enlargement File
Series VII. Authors - Additional Research Articles, Theories, and Abstracts
Series VIII. Additional Uncategorised Material
Series IX. Oversize material
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Apache Indian Tribe
  - Subseries A: Research Items
    - Aa-Aberk Journal Articles (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Aberl Journal Articles (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Aberm-Abz Journal Articles (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Ac-Af Journal Articles (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Ag-Al Journal Articles, 1901-1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Am-And Journal Articles, 1867-1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Ane-Aq Journal Articles, 1800-1987 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Ar-As-Journal Articles, 1921-1967 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - As-Az-Journal Articles, 1924-1956 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Abstracts (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Baa-Bai Journal Articles, 1838-1984 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Baj-Bal Journal Articles, 1835-1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Bal-Ban Journal Articles, 1875-1963 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - History of Arizona and New Mexico 1530-1888 by Hubert How Bancroft, 1889 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - A.F. Bandelier Journal Articles, 1890-1892 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - A.F. Bandelier Journal Articles, 1892-1937 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Bane-Banz Journal Articles, 1933-1971 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Bao-Bark Journal Articles, 1902-1946 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Barn Journal Articles, 1931-1941 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Barr-Bars Journal Articles, 1857-1931 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Bart Journal Articles, 1856-1951 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Bas-Baz Journal Articles, 1893-1987 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Bea-Beb Journal Articles, 1858-1953 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Bec-Benc Journal Articles, 1869-1973 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - A.B. Bender Journal Articles (#1), 1933-1934 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - A.B. Bender Journal Articles (#2), 1941-1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Bene-Bez Journal-Articles, 1909-1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Bia-Bif Journal Articles, 1928-1940 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Big-Biz Journal Articles, 1851-1968 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Bittle, W.E. "The Position of Kiowa-Apache in the Apachean Group", 1956 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Bla-Bly Journal Articles, 1871-1962 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Blazer Family Papers from the University of Arizona (Box 1), 1857-1966 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Blazer Family Papers from the University of Arizona (Box 3), 1857-1966 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Blazer Family Papers from the University of Arizona (Box 4), 1857-1966 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Blazer Family Papers from the University of Arizona (Box 4), 1857-1966 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Blazer's Mill Business Records from the University of New Mexico, 1871-1896 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Bloom, L.B. "Bourke on the Southwest", 1933-1938 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Boa-Bols Journal Articles, 1850-1963 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - H.E. Bolton articles (#1), 1902-1914 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - H.E. Bolton articles (#2), 1915-1917 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - H.E. Bolton articles (#3), 1920-1952 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Bolu-Bot Journal Articles, 1818-1964 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - John G. Bourke articles (#1), 1890-1891 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - John G. Bourke articles (#2), 1892 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Bov-Boz Journal Articles, 1954-1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Bra-Bri Journal Articles, 1857-1973 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Bro-Bry Journal Articles, 1894-1970 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Bu-By Journal Articles, 1900-1973 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Caa-Caq Journal Articles, 1915-1968 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Cara-Carri Journal Articles, 1854-1974 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Carro Journal Articles, 1938-1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Carru-Cars Journal Articles, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Cart-Carz Journal Articles, 1900-1968 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Cas-Caz Journal Articles, 1935-1968 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Castaneda, C.E. Our Catholic Heritage in Texas, 1519-1936, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Ce-Cham Journal Articles, 1931-1949 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Chan-Chaq Journal Articles, 1916-1956 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Char-Ci Journal Articles, 1854-1981 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Cla-Clo Journal Articles, 1852-1973 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Clum, John P. Journal Articles (#1), 1928-1929 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Clum, John P. Journal Articles (#2), 1929-1930 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Clum, John P. Journal Articles (#3), 1930-1936 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Clum, John P.- Papers at the University of Arizona, 1868-1932 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Coa-Coll Journal Articles, 1925-1974 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Colm-Colz Journal Articles, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Com-Con Journal Articles, 1902-1966 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Coo-Coq Journal Articles, 1854-1957 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Cora-Corm Journal Articles, 1924-1968 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Corn-Coz Journal Articles, 1799-1967 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Cortes, J. Articles (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Cra-Cre Journal Articles, 1863-1968 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Cri Journal Articles, 1928-1958 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Cro-Cry Journal Articles, 1886-1971 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Cu-Cy Journal Articles, 1887-1975 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Curtis, Edward Journal Articles, 1907 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Curtis, Edward, The North American Indian, 1928 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Daa-Dav Journal Articles, 1908-1972 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Daw-Daz Journal Articles, 1962-1968 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Dea-Deq Journal Articles, 1905-1951 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Der-Dez Journal Articles, 1870-1933 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - de Benavides, Fray Alonso Journal Articles, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Di Journal Articles, 1934-1978 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Doa-Dol Journal Articles, 1929-1964 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Dom-Doz Journal Articles, 1858-1973 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Dr Journal Articles, 1841-1969 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Drawing by Don Kramer and Jicarilla Calendar (Box 117, Folder 1)
    - Dua-Dum Journal Articles, 1922-1965 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Dun Journal Articles, 1930-1955 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Dunn, W.E. Journal Articles, 1911-1914 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Duo-Dy Journal Articles, 1936-1963 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Ea-Ek Journal Articles, 1847-1960 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - El Journal Articles, 1882-1975 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - El Journal Articles, 1882-1975 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Em-Et Journal Articles, 1844-1972 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Em-Et Journal Articles, 1844-1972 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Eu-Ez Journal Articles, 1838-1972 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Early Apachean Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Early Apachean Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Faa-Fat Journal Articles, 1930-1982 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Faa-Fat Journal Articles, 1930-1982 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Fall, Albert B. Papers at Huntington Library, 1861-1944 (I) (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Fall, Albert B. Papers at Huntington Library, 1861-1944 (II) (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Fall, Albert B. Papers at the University of New Mexico, 1916-1927 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Farish, Thomas E. the "History of Arizona Vol. I and II", 1915-1918 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Farish, Thomas E. the "History of Arizona Vol. III", 1916 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Farish, Thomas E. the "History of Arizona Vol. IV and V" (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Farish, Thomas E. the "History of Arizona Vol. VI and VIII", 1918 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Farish, Thomas E. the "History of Arizona Vol. VIII", 1918 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Fau-Faz Journal Articles, 1935-1974 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Fe Journal Articles, 1898-1977 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Fi-Fl Journal Articles, 1858-1964 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Foa-Forb Journal Articles, 1933-1964 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Foa-Forb Journal Articles, 1933-1964 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Forc-Foz Journal Articles, 1855-1970 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Fra-Fre Journal Articles, 1885-1971 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Fri-Fry Journal Articles, 1850-1971 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Fu-Fy Journal Articles, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Gaa-Gar Journal Articles, 1854-1977 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Gaa-Gar Journal Articles, 1854-1977 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Gas-Gatr Journal Articles, 1894-1967 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Gatewood, C.B. Papers (1850-1950) from the Arizona Pioneer's Historical Society, 1850 (I) (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Gatewood, C.B. Papers (1850-1950) from the Arizona Pioneer's Historical Society, 1850 (II) (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Gatewood, C.B. Papers (1850-1950) from the Arizona Pioneer's Historical Society, 1850 (III) (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Gatschet, Albert S. (#1), 1879-1883 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Gatschet, Albert (#2), 1884-1891 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Gatt-Gh Journal Articles, 1931-1968 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Gi-Gl Journal Articles, 1925-1979 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Goa-Gol Journal Articles, 1907-1969 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Gom-Goz Journal Articles, 1933-1970 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Gra-Gref Journal Articles, 1852-1972 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Greg-Grei Journal Articles, 1852-1968 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Grej-Gry Journal Articles, 1920-1961 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Gua-Gum Journal Articles, 1920-1968 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Gun-Guy Journal Articles, 1873-1972 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Haa-Hah Journal Articles, 1912-1968 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Hackett, C.W. "Pichardo's Treatis on the Limits of Louisiana and Texas, 1931-1946 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Hai Journal Articles (#1), 1917-1943 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Hai Journal Articles (#2), 1938-1954 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Haile, Berard Papers from the University of Arizona, Box 2, 1907-1934 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Haile, Berard Papers from the University of Arizona, Box 3, 1935-1960 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Haile, Berard Papers from the University of Arizona, Box 5 (I) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Haile, Berard Papers from the University of Arizona, Box 5 (II) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Haile, Berard Papers from the University of Arizona, Box 9 (III) (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Haj-Hal Journal Articles, 1944-1968 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Hama-Haml Journal Articles, 1884-1957 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Hamm Journal Articles, 1927-1965 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Hammond, George P. Journal Articles, 1935-1966 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Handwritten Notes for General Apachean Article (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Han-Harq Journal Articles, 1940-1970 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Harr-Harz Journal Articles, 1849-1964 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Harrington, J.P. manuscripts in the Anthropological Archives in Washington, D.C., 1935-1939 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Harrington Correspondence (#1), n.d.-1935 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Harrington Correspondence (#2), 1936-1937 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Harrington Correspondence (#3), 1938-1940 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Harrington Correspondence (#4), 1941-1944 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Harrington Correspondence (#5), 1945-1954 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Has-Haz Journal Articles, 1927-1974 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Hea-Her Journal Articles, 1903-1980 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Hes-Hex Journal Articles, 1922-1963 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Hia-Hilk Journal Articles, 1919-1938 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Hill Journal Articles, 1936-1939 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Hill Journal Articles, 1940-1944 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Hilm-Hoc Journal Articles, 1939-1960 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Hod Journal Articles, 1895-1962 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Hoe-Hoh Journal Articles, 1891-1940 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Hoijer, Harry Journal Articles (#1), 1931-1946 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Hoijer, Harry Journal Articles (#2), 1948-1975 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Hoj-Hom Journal Articles, 1929-1970 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Hon-Hoq Journal Articles, 1931-1968 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Hor-Hot Journal Articles, 1889-1970 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Hou-Hoz Journal Articles, 1844-1972 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Hr Journal Articles, 1900-1909 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Hua-Hur Journal Articles, 1862-1964 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Hus-Huz Journal Articles, 1942-1966 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Hy Journal Articles, 1952-1967 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - I Journal Articles, 1880-1972 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Ingstad, H.M. Journal Articles, 1939-1983 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Ja Journal Articles, 1877-1972 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Jea-Jehm Journal Articles, 1930-1967 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Jeffords, T.J. Papers, 1832-1914 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Jenn-Jez Journal Articles, 1933-1978 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Jicarilla Oral History, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Ji-Joh Journal Articles, 1935-1987 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Joi-Jon Journal Articles, 1890-1970 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Joo-Jy Journal Articles, 1935-1969 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Ka Journal Articles, 1904-1974 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Kea-Kelk Journal Articles, 1885-1964 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Kell Journal Articles, 1928-1980 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Kem-Kez Journal Articles, 1851-1978 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Ki Journal Article, 1919-1967 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Kluckhorn, Clyde Journal Articles (#1), 1923-1946 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Kluckhorn, Clyde Journal Articles (#2), 1947-1966 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Kn-Ko Journal Articles, 1875-1974 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Kr Journal Articles, 1928-1976 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Ku-Ky Journal Articles, 1939-1974 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Laa-Lal Journal Articles, 1891-1958 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Lam-Lanf Journal Articles, 1910-1971 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Lang-Laz Journal Articles, 1886-1953 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Lea-Leh Journal Articles, 1927-1967 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Lei-Lez Journal Articles, 1897-1971 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Li Journal Articles, 1909-1971 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Loa-Lon Journal Articles, 1930-1970 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Loo-Loz Journal Articles, 1854-1965 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Lua-Luml Journal Articles, 1964-1973 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Lumm Journal Articles, 1886-1928 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Lumn-Ly Journal Articles, 1957-1975 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Maa-Mak Journal Articles, 1875-1974 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Mal-Maq Journal Articles, 1880-1963 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Maps: Apache (Jicarilla, Chiricahua, General, Western) (Box 117, Folder 3)
    - Maps: Apache (Lipan, Mescalero) (Box 117, Folder 4)
    - Mar Journal Articles, 1866-1965 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Margry, Pierre Journal Articles, 1614-1875 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Mas-Mats Journal Articles, 1885-1957 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Matthews, Washington Journal Articles, 1883-1888 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Matt Journal Articles, 1889-1907 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Matu-Maz Journal Articles, 1894-1968 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Mazzanovich, A. Papers, 1886 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - McA-McCi Journal Articles, 1868-1965 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - McL-McD Journal Articles, 1907-1970 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - McL-McD Journal Articles, 1907-1970 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - McE-McZ Journal Articles, 1918-1962 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Mea-Meq Journal Articles, 1926-1968 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Mer-Mez Journal Articles, 1875-1972 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Mia-Milk Journal Articles, 1897-1911 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Mill-Miz Journal Articles, 1896-1984 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Moa-Moom Journal Articles, 1899-1969 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Montezuma, Carlos Papers from the University of Arizona, 1899-1922 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Moon-Mooq Journal Articles, 1872-1898 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Moor-Mooz Journal Articles, 1914-1977 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Mop-Moz Journal Articles, 1822-1970 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Mua-Mum Journal Articles, 1922-1965 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Mun-Murq Journal Articles, 1937-1973 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Murr-Muz Journal Articles, 1951-1983 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Mya-Myz Journal Articles, 1960-1971 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Naa-Neh Journal Articles, 1952-1980 (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Nei-Nel Journal Articles, 1936-1973 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Neighbours, K.F. (Thesis), 1955 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Nem-Nez Journal Articles, 1938-1971 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Ni Journal Articles, 1890-1934 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - No-Ny Journal Articles, 1937-1971 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Oa-Om Journal Articles, 189-1966 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - On-Oz Journal Articles, 1864-1980 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Paa-Paq Journal Articles, 1865-1965 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Palmer, Edward manuscripts from the University of Arizona, 1865-1889 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Para-Parr Journal Articles, 1855-1967 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Pars-Paz Journal Articles, 1905-1980 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Pea-Perr Journal Articles, 1919-1978 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Pers-Ph Journal Articles, 1878-1967 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Photo Information (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Pi Journal Articles, 1786-1980 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Plant Names and Identification: Mescalero-Chiricahua and Jicarilla (Box 117, Folder 2)
    - Po Journal Articles, 1888-1966 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Poston, Charles "History of the Apaches", 1886 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Pr-Py Journal Articles, 1883-1975 (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - Q Journal Articles, 1854-1966 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Raa-Rax Journal Articles, 1904-1992 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - "Ramona Days", 1887 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Ray-Raz Journal Articles, 1845-1966 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Rea-Red Journal Articles, 1901-1960 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Reagan, Albert B. "The White Mountain Apache Indians.. .", 1901 (I) (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Reagan, Albert B. "The White Mountain Apache Indians.. .", 1901 (II) (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Reagan, Albert B. "The White Mountain Apache Indians.. .", 1901 (III) (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Ree Journal Articles (#1), 1941-1954 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Ree Journal Articles (#2), 1937-1938 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Ree Journal Articles (#3), 1933-1949 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Ree Journal Articles (#4), 1950-1964 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Ref-Rib Journal Articles, 1858-1974 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Ric Journal Articles (#1), 1869-1963 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Ric Journal Articles (#2), 1934 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Ric Journal Articles (#3), 1942-1971 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Rid-Rif Journal Articles, 1919-1984 (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Ris-Riz Journal Articles, 1878-1946 (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Roa-Rol Journal Articles, 1912-1955 (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Rom-Roz Journal Articles, 1864-1978 (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - Russell, Frank-Jicarilla Apache vocabulary, 1898 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Ru-Ry Journal Articles, 1886-1980 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Saa-Sab Journal Articles, 1935 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Sac-Saq Journal Articles, 1915-1968 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Sar-Sce Journal Articles, 1934-1982 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Scha-Sche Journal Articles, 1945-1972 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Schm-Schn Journal Articles, 1927-1966 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Schoa-Schon Journal Articles, 1930-1984 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Schoo-Schoz Journal Articles, 1851-1853 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Schur-Schy Journal Articles, 1873-1972 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Sci-Scy Journal Articles, 1928-1962 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Se-Shek Journal Articles, 1855-1985 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Shel-Shy Journal Articles, 1887-1964 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Si-Sj Journal Articles, 1849-1975 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Sk-Sme Journal Articles, 1872-1968 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - Smi Journal Articles (#1), 1928-1970 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Smi Journal Articles (#2), 1900-1972 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Smo-Son Journal Articles, 1939-1968 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Soo-Soz Journal Articles, 1904-1964 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Sp-Sq Journal Articles, 1921-1971 (Box 23, Folder 4)